# Arman Zharmagambetov, PhD candidate

CONTACT Information Address: Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, School of Engineering

University of California, Merced

5200 N. Lake Road, Merced, CA 95343, USA

E-mail: azharmagambetov@ucmerced.edu

WWW: http://graduatestudents.ucmerced.edu/azharmagambetov/

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research focuses on Machine Learning and Mathematical Optimization. Specifically, my primary area of expertise is in learning decision trees and tree-based models; and their applications in various areas, such as: supervised learning, neural networks compression, dimensionality reduction, semi-supervised learning, model interpretability, etc.

**EDUCATION** 

### University of California, Merced, CA

Ph.D., Machine Learning and Optimization, Expected: Fall 2022

• Advisor: Miguel Á. Carreira-Perpiñán

# International Information Technologies University (IITU), Almaty, Kazakhstan

M.S., Mathematical and Computer modeling, Jul 2017

- M.S. thesis: Numerical methods for solving Fredholm Integral-Differential equations.
- Advisor: Dulat S. Dzhumabaev

B.S. (summa cum laude), Mathematical and Computer modeling, Jul 2015

• B.S. thesis: Statistical methods for measuring word similarities in Kazakh language.

Professional Experience

#### Applied Scientist Intern

May 2021 to Aug 2021

Amazon, Cambridge, Massachusetts.

Amazon Alexa. Hosts: Qingming Tang, Ming Sun.

Improved Representation Learning for Acoustic Event Classification Using Tree-structured Ontology (ICASSP '22): link to the paper.

## **Applied Scientist Intern**

May 2020 to Aug 2020

Amazon, Seattle, Washington.

Supply Chain Optimization Team (SCOT). Hosts: Joyjit Roy, Henry Dai.

Designed a data-driven approach in forecasting outbound network flow for Amazon facilities.

## Research/Teaching Assistant

Aug 2017 to present

University of California, Merced

Member of the machine learning research group.

TA for the following courses: Algorithm Design and Analysis; Object Oriented Programming.

#### ML Engineer

Jul 2016 to Jul 2017

Kaspi bank, Almaty, Kazakhstan

Developed AI/ML based solutions for financial sector: default prediction, fraud detection, recommender systems, etc.

## ML Engineer

Jul 2014 to Feb 2017

Alem Research LLP, Almaty, Kazakhstan

Designed and deployed ML models for natural language processing tasks: sentiment classification of news articles, clustering documents in Kazakh and Russian languages.

## Publications [Google Scholar page]

- 1. [NeurIPS] A. Zharmagambetov and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Semi-Supervised Learning with Decision Trees: Graph Laplacian Tree Alternating Optimization. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, to appear, 2022.
- 2. [AISTATS] A. Zharmagambetov and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Learning Interpretable, Tree-Based Projection Mappings for Nonlinear Embeddings. International Conf. on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics, 2022.
- 3. [EMNLP] A. Zharmagambetov, M. Gabidolla and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Softmax Tree: An Accurate, Fast Classifier When the Number of Classes Is Large. Conf. on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, 2021.
- 4. [ICML] A. Zharmagambetov and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Smaller, More Accurate Regression Forests Using Tree Alternating Optimization. International Conf. on Machine Learning, 2020.
- [ICASSP] A. Zharmagambetov, Q. Tang, C.-C. Kao, Q. Zhang, M. Sun, V. Rozgic, J. Droppo, C. Wang. Improved Representation Learning for Acoustic Event Classification Using Tree-structured Ontology. IEEE International Conf. on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing, 2022.
- [ICASSP] A. Zharmagambetov and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Learning a Tree of Neural Nets. IEEE International Conf. on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing, 2021.
- 7. Y. Idelbayev, A. Zharmagambetov, M. Gabidolla and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Faster Neural Net Inference via Forests of Sparse Oblique Decision Trees. 2021.
- 8. [IJCNN] A. Zharmagambetov and M. Gabidolla and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Improved Boosted Regression Forests Through Non-Greedy Tree Optimization. International Joint Conf. on Neural Networks, 2021.
- 9. [IJCNN] A. Zharmagambetov and S. S. Hada and M. Gabidolla and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Non-Greedy Algorithms for Decision Tree Optimization: An Experimental Comparison. International Joint Conf. on Neural Networks, 2021.
- [ICIP] A. Zharmagambetov and M. Gabidolla and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Improved Multiclass AdaBoost for Image Classification: The Role of Tree Optimization. IEEE International Conf. on Image Processing, 2021.
- 11. [ICIP] A. Zharmagambetov and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. A Simple, Effective Way to Improve Neural Net Classification: Ensembling Unit Activations with a Sparse Oblique Decision Tree. IEEE International Conf. on Image Processing, 2021.
- 12. [ICIP] S.S.Hada, M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán, A. Zharmagambetov. Understanding and Manipulating Neural Net Features Using Sparse Oblique Classification Trees. IEEE International Conf. on Image Processing, 2021.
- 13. [FODS] M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán and A. Zharmagambetov. Ensembles of bagged TAO trees consistently improve over Random Forests, AdaBoost and Gradient Boosting. ACM-IMS Foundations of Data Science Conf., 2020.
- 14. S. Narynov and A. Zharmagambetov. On One Approach of Solving Sentiment Analysis Task for Kazakh and Russian Languages Using Deep Learning. Int. Conf. on Computational Collective Intelligence (ICCCI), Halkidiki, Greece, 2016. Springer.

15. A. A. Pak, S. Narynov, A. Zharmagambetov, Sh. Sagyndykova, Zh. Kenzhebayeva. The Method of Synonyms Extraction from Unannotated Corpus. In proceedings of the IEEE 3rd Int. Conf. on Digital Information, Networking, and Wireless Communications (DINWC), Moscow, Russia, 2015.

# Posters and EXTENDED ABSTRACTS

- 1. [BayLearn] M. Gabidolla and A. Zharmagambetov and M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán. Boosted Sparse Oblique Decision Trees. Bay Area Machine Learning Symposium, 2020.
- 2. [BayLearn] M. Á. Carreira-Perpiñán and A. Zharmagambetov. Fast Model Compression. Bay Area Machine Learning Symposium, 2018.

# Professional ACTIVITIES

Reviewer for the following conferences:

- Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), since 2020.
- International Conf. Machine Learning (ICML), since 2020.
- AAAI Conf. on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), since 2020.
- International Conf. on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), since 2021.
- International Conf. on Learning Representations (ICLR), since 2021.

#### AWARDS

• D&I travel award from EMNLP 2021 organizing committee	November 2021
• UC Merced Outstanding Teaching Award (\$1000)	May 2019
• UC Merced Chancellor's Graduate Fellowship (\$16000)	August 2017
• ML Challenge winner (programming contest, Almaty, KZ)	January 2015
• Hackday winner (projects contest, Almaty, KZ)	April 2013

## INVITED TALKS

• IICT, Almaty, Kazakhstan

Jan 2022

Topic: "TAO: Efficient and Universal Algorithm to Train Decision Trees and Tree-Based Models."

- IITU, Almaty, Kazakhstan Dec 2018
- Applied mathematics department seminar. Topic: "Modern approaches in neural net compression." Mar 2017 • Artificial Intelligence Day, Almaty, Kazakhstan

Topic: "Sentiment Analysis Task for Kazakh and Russian Languages Using Deep Learning"

• KBTU IT talks, Almaty, Kazakhstan Jul 2016 Topic: "Machine learning in banks"

- TECHNICAL SKILLS Programming languages: Python, Matlab, Java, C/C++, C#;
  - Operating Systems: Linux, MacOS, Windows;
  - Frameworks: pytorch, tensorflow, keras, scikit-learn, numpy, libsym/liblinear, etc.;

#### LANGUAGES

Kazakh (native), Russian (fluent), English (fluent)